RYAN S.L. CARPENTER

SOFTWARE ENGINEER & ENTREPRENEUR

ryan.sl.carpenter@gmail.com • Hong Kong • rslc.us

SKILLS Frontend Web Development

I have worked more than seven years with both React.js and different versions of Angular. I am also familiar with Vue.JS and React Native, through smaller projects. I focus on process improvement in any team I join; that may mean improving test architecture, integrating documentation tools into feature development, or optimizing software builds. I find every opportunity to improve code as I work on it—refactoring, modularizing, and updating architectures to make projects more maintainable for the developers that follow me.

Full-Stack Web Development

I have built the complete tech stack of multiple corporate-ready web and hybrid mobile apps. I have worked both on my own and by managing a developer team. I prefer an agile approach, allowing better product feedback from a fast release cycle. I am well-versed in multiple front-end and back-end JavaScript frameworks. As an entrepreneur, I have also managed our DevOps, including continuous integration tools and serverless architectures.

Software Product Management

I have steered several software products from concept, through development and testing, to ongoing operations. I enjoy tackling a complex problem, imagining how a solution can be applied, then carefully managing the steps to build it effectively and efficiently.

Team Leadership

Through my career with small transnational companies, I have had the opportunity to manage multilingual teams that have been both on-site and remote. In addition to organizing their development work, I mentored my teams and ensured that their skill sets were consistently growing to support our future needs and their professional development. In my extracurricular activities, I have also taken leadership roles in community groups, including acting as Team Captain for our local masters swimming team (100+ members).

EXPERIENCE

Easyship • Lead Frontend Developer

NOV 2020 - PRESENT, HONG KONG

Managed our frontend team as we expanded both our product offerings and global market share. Grew the team from a single office to span three continents. Spearheaded efforts to internationalize our apps, migrate from AngularJS to React.js, and improve performance across the board. Helped Easyship triple the number of shipments sold on the platform, growing net sales by 35%.

Emotics • Co-founder / Tech Lead

MAR 2017 - OCT 2020, HONG KONG

Founded Emotics to solve some clear failings in corporate learning software. Used webcam snapshots to approach a solution from two directions: by gathering real-time, subconscious feedback on the content that each learner is viewing and by leveraging facial recognition tech and behavior analysis to identify "cheating" behaviors. Led Emotics' tech development by building an SDK to integrate with client software, an API to collect data and serve results, and a front-end website for compliance managers to view analytics and review alerts. Maintained infrastructure, tests, and documentation for enterprise-level reliability and issue response. Emotics was recognized as an innovator in this space by Bloomberg News, banking industry groups, and Hong Kong regulators.

GBST • App Strategy Consultant / Product Manager

JAN 2015 - APR 2016, HONG KONG

Formed a strategy for integrating mobile apps into GBST's financial services software. Hired and remotely-managed development team based in Vietnam. Built prototypes and pitched them to GBST clients, following agile processes for frequent releases.

Exicon • Operations Transformation Project

APR 2014 - NOV 2014, HONG KONG

Identified gaps in and reorganized the company budget to successfully reduce costs and increase revenues. Created a pricing strategy to be attractive to both low-touch users and large enterprise clients. Established team metrics and the systems to monitor them.

LoadStar / Savi Networks • Program Manager

SEP 2007- MAR 2014, HONG KONG / CALIFORNIA

Directed hardware development of our shipping-container-monitoring product through a new Chinese manufacturing partner. Supported the management of our 30-person software development team contracted in Beijing.

Lockheed Martin • TSAT Mission Operations System (TMOS) Risk Manager

SEP 2004 - SEP 2007, SAN JOSE, CALIFORNIA

Managed authors of a 500+ page bid-winning, proposal document for a large defense contract. Directed the creation of mitigation plans that would eliminate 90% of program risk over contract lifetime and monitored their execution.

EDUCATION

Stanford University • M.S. Aeronautics and Astronautics

2005 - 2007, PALO ALTO, CALIFORNIA

Through Stanford's Center for Professional Development, I completed their master's degree curriculum on evenings and weekends, while working full-time at Lockheed Martin.

Harvey Mudd College • B.S. Engineering

2000 - 2004, CLAREMONT, CALIFORNIA

HMC is a prestigious liberal arts college focused on engineering, math, and sciences. It is collocated with four other undergraduate schools, forming the Claremont Colleges.

pwc Scale Program • Startup Accelerator

2020, LONDON, UNITED KINGDOM (REMOTE)

StartupBootCamp • Startup Accelerator

2019, MELBOURNE, AUSTRALIA

Lockheed Martin Engineering Dev. Program • Corporate Leadership Program

2005-2008, SAN JOSE, CALIFORNIA

INTERESTS

I am a father to a precocious 5-year-old daughter and a husband to a talented, dedicated swimming director. I had a long career in swimming including leadership roles on both my college and adult (masters) teams. Living in Hong Kong has also introduced me to dragon boat racing and an a cappella singing group where I taught myself to arrange our own songs for four voices. I enjoy combining my web development skills with my interest in cartography to create unique, interactive maps, from Hong Kong public transit, to the voyages of Zheng He, to the world of Game of Thrones.

AWARDS

Emotics was recognized by the government of Hong Kong, winning the HKICT Silver Award in 2018, and Regulation Asia. Emotics has also won acceptance into competitive business accelerators like Seedstars, Startupbootcamp, and pwc Scale.

At Lockheed Martin, I was one of 5% of new employees to participate in the Engineering Leadership Development Program.

I am proud to have helped my dragon boat team win the Stanley International Championships as well as earn medals and break records with my swimming teams at NCAA Division III Nationals and FINA World Masters Championships. At home, I have received an honorary mug as World's Okayest Dad.

HR SEARCH TERM LIST

This resume has been optimized to be read by human beings, but I know it will be run through recruiting software as well. Some tech search terms relevant to me:

Node.js, React, AngularJS, Vue.JS, React Native, Cordova, JavaScript, TypeScript, AWS, Elastic Beanstalk, RDS, Rekognition, CloudFront, Lambda, API, SDK, PostgreSQL, MySQL, CircleCI, GitHub Actions, Postman, Jira, kanban, agile